[SPEAKER_00] I'm just going to quickly repeat what I said, that basically we're going to go over the important parts of the previous lesson. Whatever you did not get with regards to مُبْتَدَة and خَبَر, the subject and the predicate, don't worry about it, we'll go over it later, inshallah. For now, I just want you guys to focus on the aspect that we learned about, ال, and the definite and indefinite. And I'm going to, inshallah, very quickly re-go over that part, and inshallah we'll go through a bunch of examples, so that the concept is solidified in our minds. So don't worry too much if you didn't understand what happened in the previous lesson, inshallah. We'll go over the important stuff this time, and the other stuff is obviously very important, but we don't necessarily need to know it now. So, if you understood it, that's good, otherwise, inshallah, we'll go over it again later, so don't worry about it. So one thing I do think would be good to know now, is that distinguishing between the اسم, the فَرْن, and the حَوْف. Right, so اسم we explained is a noun, as the brother mentioned. Now, a noun in Arabic, an اسم,
[SPEAKER_00] entails what? Somebody mentioned? Person. Person, okay, good. Place. Place, okay. Thing. Idea. Idea, okay. Adjective. Adjective, good. And we said adverb as well, but it's not so important, but yes, adverb. So these are six things that the word اسم includes. Alright, then we went to a فَرْن. What is a فَرْن? Word. Okay, and what does a verb entail? An action. An action, right? Something that you do. And that, what type of meaning does it give? It gives the sense of time, a time, right? So you understand a time period that something happened in the past, present, or future, right? And then we talked about the حرف, which would be translated to the word particle, which we don't fully understand what that really means, because we haven't studied English grammar. Maybe some of you have, in so much detail. But what does it entail? It would just be like a miscellaneous category. But these are words that don't have a meaning. In and of themselves, they're rather words used to
[SPEAKER_00] connect different اسم and فَرْن. Yes, it doesn't mean that they have absolutely no meaning, but their meaning changes relative to the اسم and the فَرْن that they're connected to, right? We did mention that the vast majority of what we learned so far, they are what? Of the three categories, they're which one? اسم, right? And there's only two حرفs that we learned so far, which are? و and ا, good. حمزة الاستفحام, which is used to ask questions. And و, which is used to explain, to add things together, to say و. Basically, it means and. Okay. Now, the thing that I wanted you to remember from yesterday's lesson is the difference between a word that has ال and a word that just has تنوين, right? So what was the difference between the two? Somebody explain to me very briefly. Specific and nonspecific. There's different ways to say it. You could say specific or nonspecific.
[SPEAKER_00] You could say known or unknown. You could say definite or indefinite, right? These are three different ways to kind of explain the same concept. But we explained this concept a little further when we said that if you say that, oh, a man, I met a man today. So that's understood. If you're telling somebody, I met a man, that's understood to the person you're talking to that this man was some random person. It's not somebody who you knew from before. It's just an unspecified person. And that person... That person's identity is not really important. The point is that you met someone. But now, if you say, oh, I met that guy today, the man today, then it's assumed that the person you're talking to already knows who you're talking about. And if they don't, then you'll be like, wait, what man, right? Because you're saying the man, so you're assuming that I know which person you're talking about. Similarly, we gave the example of a book, right? For example, I mentioned that some brother asked me the other day, can you bring a book from your library? I said, which book? He said, any book, you know. I just want to read some more.
[SPEAKER_00] I guess he was bored, so he wants to read more about Islamic things. And so he said, can you just bring me a book? So now, when he says a book, that means any book in the library will fit the bill. So it's not specified. It's general, right? So it's unspecified, or it's something which is unknown. So that's why you would use a tanween. You would say kitabun, right? You wouldn't say al-kitab, because then you're specifying, a specific book. But now let's say, he specified a book. Can you borrow me this book, Dursu al-Lughat al-Arabiya, Volume 2? I really need it for class tomorrow. Then I came to the masjid the next day. He would ask me what? Hal indaka al-kitab? Do you have the book? In English, you would say, did you have the book? He's saying the, because it's a specific book that he had asked for. Everybody got the distinguishing between the two? You understand the difference between the two? A book and the book. A book and the book, right? So that's the very same difference between something
[SPEAKER_00] which has a tanween, which is two dhammas put together, and al, right? It's not going into the lesson. So, So when we say alhamdulillah, So are we saying we say all praises to Allah, right? So then why are we saying, Alhamdulillah, and you can also say, Alhamdulillah, No. That's a good question. So the word al means something specific, right? But then on top of that, it can mean other meanings based on the context, right? Sometimes it can mean, al refers to all of the people from that category. For example, if you say, Al-insanu, man. Like sometimes you say, the human being. You're talking about a specific human being. But sometimes when you're saying like in English, you say, man is a strange creature. For example, right? And you're not talking about a specific human being. You're talking about man in general
[SPEAKER_00] as a category, right? So same way you're saying, Alhamdulillah, you're saying the entire category of alhamdulillah, of praise belongs to Allah. So you're saying, that's why you're saying all praises to Allah. So that's specific because every single, all the aspects of alhamdulillah, of praise are included in that. So that's why it's specific. If you just say, alhamdulillah, praise to Allah, and that would be only a specific, it would only be a one random praise out of all the different praises that could be given to Allah. You're just saying, a praise is due to Allah, right? But that's not what you're saying. You're saying the praise, all of the praise is due to Allah, is deserved by Allah . You understand? So, okay. We'll go through examples from the Qur'an inshaAllah. We have multiple brothers, they mentioned that when we have examples from the Qur'an, they feel like they understand better, and it's easier to come to it. So we do have some in store right now. But let's just look at the lesson again, inshaAllah, just so we make sure we understood the core
[SPEAKER_00] concept of the lesson, right? So we read yesterday, بَيْتٌ الْبَيْتُ Another difference we highlighted is that, whenever al comes on a word, what's the golden rule? If the word, if al comes on a word, what's the golden rule? Tanween will go away, right? You can never have a word that has al and tanween, right? I'll give you a million dollars if you find such a word, right? You can't just write it on it. You can't just write it on a word and say that, you know. It doesn't count. I mean like correctly written word, right? So yeah, that rule is there all the time, right? There's no exceptions. That, you can never have tanween on a word that has al. Okay, so now when you say بَيْتٌ, that means a house. الْبَيْتُ means a specific house, right? كِتَابٌ, as an example we mentioned, means any random book, a book. Then الْكِتَابُ means a specific book. قَلَمٌ means a pen. الْقَلَمُ means that specific pen, right? So for example,
[SPEAKER_00] this, you could just call it a pen even if it's a marker. And you would use the word قَلَم in Arabic anyways, even for a marker. Let's say, my brother, Mustafa, every day, every time we have class, he brings me the same pen, right? So in the beginning of the class, I ask him, do you have a marker? هَلْ عَنْدَكَ قَلَمٌ Do you have a marker that I can use for this class, right? But since we started using the same specific marker for every class, now, when it's class time, now we'll ask him, هَلْ عَنْدَكَ الْقَلَمُ الْقَلَمُ, right? Do you have the pen, the marker that we're using? Because now it's become specified, now it's become something that, you know, we know, right? Something that's known. So that's why you start using the word الْ. Everybody get it? Okay. Then جَمَلٌ, a camel. Then الْجَمَلُ So for example, the camel I showed you guys last class, right? That's just جَمَلٌ, that's just a camel to you guys. But to me, it was the camel, right?
[SPEAKER_00] Because I was there, I actually saw it, right? So if you're referring to a specific camel, then it's الْجَمَلُ. Otherwise, it's جَمَلٌ. Okay, now this was the homework to translate these things. I actually think I translated this in class, right? الْقَلَمُ مَكْسُرٌ The pen is broken. And we talked about is, again, that relates to the concept. The concept of مُبْتَدًا قَبْرًا which don't worry about it right now. But as long as you get the concept that in this type of structured sentence, you have a word that has الْ and then it ends with a word that has تَنْوِين on it, then you translate it like this. The pen is broken. The door is open. The boy is sitting and the teacher is standing, right? Once we move a little forward, we'll go into the details of that and what the rule behind it, even though we already did last class, but no need to worry about it. If you didn't get it, inshaAllah, we'll go over it again and it'll stick, inshaAllah. The point here is
[SPEAKER_00] that this is a full sentence now. If you was to say, for example, الْقَلَمُ الْمَكْسُرُ the broken pen, is that in English, for example, if I was to say the broken pen, is that a full sentence? No, right? It requires some information about the pen to complete the sentence, right? For example, then you would have to say the broken pen is on the table, right? Now it's a complete sentence, right? You get it? But when it's in this form, الْقَلَمُ الْمَكْسُرُ then it's a complete sentence. The pen is broken. You get it? Right? Okay. الْبَابُ مَفْتُوحٌ The door is open. الْوَلَدُ جَارِسٌ The boy is sitting. الْمُدَرِّسُ وَاقِفٌ And the teacher is standing. الْكِتَابُ جَدِيدٌ جديد means new, okay? So add that to your vocabulary list, and inshaAllah, memorize it till Monday. جديد, right? Any place that جديد comes in the Qur'an?
[SPEAKER_00] Very good, mashaAllah. بَلْهُمْ فِي لَبَسٍ مِّنْ خَلْقٍ جَدِيدٍ Sorry, you asked for five seconds. بَلْهُمْ فِي لَبَسٍ مِّنْ خَلْقٍ جَدِيدٍ Allah is talking about these disbelievers who keep on bringing up doubts about the creation of man, that he will be recreated after he dies, meaning he'll be brought back to life. So Allah is saying he is in confusion. لَبْس means confusion. فِي خَلْقٍ جَدِيدٍ With regards to a new creation. خَلْق means creation. جَدِيد means new. Meaning he's in confusion about this new creation that he will be created again. That's called جَدِيد, new. You get it? So you guys understand? خَلْق جَدِيد. Very good, mashaAllah. Alright, so جَدِيد means something that is new. Alright, so the book is new. وَالْقَلَمُ قَدِيمٌ And the pen is old. قَدِيمٌ means old. Any example of قَدِيم in the Qur'an? Okay, I
[SPEAKER_00] don't think there's any in the Qur'an. I'm just testing you guys. Alright. الْحِمَارُ صَغِيرٌ وَالْحِصَانُ كَبِيرٌ The donkey is... What does صَغِيرٌ mean? Small. Right. وَالْحِصَانُ كَبِيرٌ And the horse is big. These adjectives especially, you should definitely... Okay, if you're not so interested, you're like, I don't really care about how to say donkey or horse. I just want to understand the Qur'an. Even though we did explain in previous lesson that these words do come in the Qur'an. Okay, vocabulary like that may not be so important. But adjectives like these that are coming up, for example, جَدِيد is new. That's a very common word in Arabic. قَدِيم means old. And صَغِير is a very common word in Arabic, which means صَغِير means small, right? Any place in the Qur'an that comes صَغِير. Two.
[SPEAKER_00] Don't you say صَغِير is a big word or something else? مَا أَعْمَدُ الَّذُينَ وَمَا أَrittَوا فَرْضَكُمْ This word comes often also. Imagine talking about somebody at a cafe. Let's say you shot the light газ hacked your room And this person would probably be screwed a hole in your rude face. So you could get Black-fed. Answers, we'd showauf after which catalog ofаться if you underneath. Even a small thing Nor a big thing كبيرة إلا أحصاص Both the words صغير And كبير Both come in the same ayah Small thing And a big thing This book does not leave A single one of those things Right Another ayah In which صغير And كبير Both It comes in both It comes in surah Yunus Okay I can't remember In surah Yunus But I do remember in Surah Al-Qamar I remember MashaAllah very good وكل صغير وكبير مستطر Allah is saying that Every small thing And
[SPEAKER_00] every big thing They are all written down Meaning every single thing that you do Is written Either that can be meant to understood That it is written In your book of deeds Or it can be understood That it was written in the past In اللوح المحفوظ When Allah had the angels write The qadr The destiny for the entire You know To the end of times It was all written Every small thing صغير وكبير Right وكل صغير وكبير مستطر It has been written Okay So the point is صغير and كبير These are easy words But they come very often In the Quran In the hadith as well So صغير means small Another famous ayah وقل رب رحمهما كما ربياني صغيرا Right You're making du'a Allah is telling us to make du'a For our parents Who have raised us Small When we were small In a state that we were small Right So since we were young We were small Our parents were taking care of us And so Allah is telling us To make du
[SPEAKER_00] 'a for their mercy So صغير Okay So الحمار صغير The donkey is small والحصان كبير Alright الكرسي مكسور I know this was homework For those who did it You can probably like Okay this is superfluous But many of the brothers Didn't do the homework So we're just going over it quickly Okay But inshallah we hope That all the brothers Start doing the homework Because if you don't do the homework You'll see a very clear difference Between those who are doing the homework And those who are not doing the homework And unfortunately Those who lag behind And they're lazy from the get-go Then after a few classes They're like I'm not even getting much out of it So I'm just going to drop out So it's like a self-fulfilling prophecy So let's not be from those people Right We don't want to drop out We don't want our numbers to decrease Right Again it's not about the numbers It's about each specific person Each one of us Do we want to Let this goal of learning Arabic go Right So easily When we're literally in our grasp All we literally have to do Is keep attending classes Do the homework Not much time we have to give Every week Or are
[SPEAKER_00] we just going to be lazy And let our laziness overcome So yeah Al-Qursi is in Urdu as well Actually that wasn't the first lesson So you guys should know it already What does Qursi mean? Chair Chair Maxoorun means? Broken So how do you translate the sentence exactly? The chair is broken The chair is broken Okay Next Al-Mindeel wasikhun Somebody from Gen Z What is Al-Mindeel? Haroon What's a Mindeel? Handkerchief Handkerchief You know what a handkerchief is? It's like the map that you can use Have you ever seen one in your life? No No? Okay Alright So So So Al-Mindeel wasikhun What does that mean? Dirty Dirty Dirty Okay Alright Al-Ma'u baarid The water is cold The water is cold Right Baarid
[SPEAKER_00] Does the word baarid come? La baaridin wa la kareem La baaridin wa la kareem Very good Mashallah Wa dhillim min yahmum la baaridin wa la kareem So Allah is talking about the horrors of the hellfire Right And He's talking about the smoke that's going to come It is la baaridin It is not cold Wa la kareem Nor is it something which is easy upon a person or soft I don't know how we would exactly translate it in this context More or less But the point is baarid means cold So Allah is describing the fire of Jahannam that is not The punishment of Jahannam It is not La baarid It is not something which is cold So Al-Ma'u baaridin The water is cold That's actually a beautiful dua of the Prophet Oh Allah make the Allah maja'al hubbaka ahabba ilayya minal ma'il baarid Oh Allah make your love more beloved to me than cold water Right What a beautiful dua Right Because cold water is something which is very beloved to you Especially when you're thirsty on a hot day Drinking cold water How nice does that feel So
[SPEAKER_00] the Prophet ﷺ is making dua Oh Allah make your love more beloved to me than Al-Ma'il baaridin Cold water Right How beautiful is that So Al-Ma'u baaridin The water is cold Al-Qamaroo jameeloo Al-Qamar There's a whole surah which is Which is named after Al-Qamar What does Al-Qamar mean? The moon The moon Okay Al-Qamar specifically is not just any moon Because the moon has many phases Al-Qamar is referring to The 14th night The full moon Right So that's what Al-Qamar refers to Right Whereas a crescent When the moon is towards the end or beginning It's called what? Al-Hilal That's something we might have heard Hilal For example we have the Hilal committee So Hilal means crescent But when the moon is full Then it's called Al-Qamar So Al-Qamaroo jameeloo But the Sahabi said that Oh Samura I forgot the name of the Sahabi but Jabir bin Samura said that I
[SPEAKER_00] was looking at the Prophet On a moonlit night I started looking at him And at the Al-Qamar The moon He was To me more beautiful and better Than Al-Qamar Than the moon Right So Al-Qamar means The moon Okay Jameeloo Jameel means Beautiful Beautiful Okay Then Al-Baytoo qareeboon Wal-Masjidoo ba'eedoon Okay The house is near and the masjid is far Very good Mashallah The house is near Qareeboon Means Close Wal-Masjidoo ba'eedoon And the masjid is Far Okay Where is an ayah of the Quran Which has both Qareeb and ba'eed Well It's not one ayah It's two ayahs Right next to each other Hufa'ad Come on What What What is one ayah That has both Qareeban and ba'eedan
[SPEAKER_00] Both Next to each other Come on We have There's not only two Hufa'ads There's a lot of other Hufa'ads too Shaykh Tamim Hard time Say Innahum Yaloonahu ba'eedan Mashallah Very good Mashallah You deserve a prize for that Innahum yaloonahu ba'eeda wa narahu qareeba Right So Allah is talking about the disbelievers They see that the hereafter is something which is far away Like it's not gonna happen It's something which is far away But Allah is saying Wa narahu qareeba But we know it To be something which is close Right So ba'eeda qareeba Right You see the juxtaposition So Ba'eed Means far And qareeb means close Qareeb means close in Urdu as well Right Okay A beautiful ayah also in the Qur'an Allah says Wa idha sa'alaka a'ibadi anni fa inni qareeb When My slaves ask you about me Talk to the Prophet Then tell them that I am
[SPEAKER_00] qareeb I am close Okay So the word qareeb means close Okay One question Just to understand So The word we learned Hazar Was for No What's the word Zalik Zalik Sorry Zalik So Can we fit zalika here or no Like because it says Al baytu Al baytu qareebun Wa zalika masjidil bayt You would say Wa zalika al masjidu ba'eedun And that masjid is far You could say it like that if you want to Yeah You could say Hatha al baytu qareebun Wa zalika al masjidu ba'eedun Yeah If you want to fit Hatha al baytu qareebun You could fit it If it's something that You're pointing at Then you would say Hatha al baytu qareebun Wa zalika al masjidu ba'eedun Okay Next Al hajaru thakeelun Al hajar means Stone Rock
[SPEAKER_00] Rock or stone Thakeelun means Heavy Heavy Okay Wal waraq khafifun Al waraq means Paper Paper Al waraq means Paper Al waraq means And khafif Light Light Light Okay Very good inshaAllah Allah says Faman thakulat Thaqulat mawazinuhu faulaikahum nukheerun Whoever's scale of deeds are heavy Then they are the successful ones So that comes from the same word Thaqeel Thaqulat mawazinuhu It comes from the same word Thaqeel So thakeel means heavy Then they are the successful ones Then Allah says Waman khaffat mawazinuhu The person whose scale of deeds are light Khaffat They come from the same word as Khafeef Khaffat Khafeef So faman khaffat mawazinuhu Then Allah says that they are the losers So khafeef means light And thakeel means heavy Al labanu harun Right We talked about Al
[SPEAKER_00] laban means Milk Milk Harun means Okay So a similar word to har Comes from the Quran Qul naaru jahannama ashaddu harra Right The hypocrite was saying Oh don't go out in the path of Allah in the heat So Allah says La tanfiru fil harr Don't go out in the heat Then Allah says Qul naaru jahannama ashaddu harra He told the prophet to say to them That the fire of hell is har Ashaddu harra Okay Al qamisu nazifun Al qamisu means Shirt Nazifun means Clean Clean Okay Alright so we finished the vocabulary Of this lesson so far And you guys were supposed to already do it So do the tamareen that are mentioned here Tamareen are the practice examples So over here it says The first one says Iqra waqtub ma'adabti awakhiril kalimat What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_00] It means read and write Along with Dabt means like putting the haraka At the end of the words You know what haraka means? Haraka means either Fatha Kasra Or dhamma That's called haraka Right So if I ask you what's the haraka on this You would say Either kasra Or fatha Or dhamma Right So it's saying Put the haraka at the end of each word Right Basically what are they trying to test you on? They're trying to test you on If you know that golden rule that I told you That you get a million dollars If you prove me wrong Right Which is What's the Yeah If al and tanween cannot come together Right So they're trying to test you on that rule So they're trying to see Do you know If there's a No al on there Then you have a tanween And if there is an al Then you only have one dhamma Or not That's the main thing They're testing you on this homework So just It's easy right So just finish Do the homework InshaAllah do that Basically just write down the word And at the end write Is it a one
[SPEAKER_00] dhamma Or two That's the main thing That's being tested in this whole thing But obviously writing the Arabic helps you practice as well Then the second homework is The second tanween is Read and write Right Over here it's similar You write this down Read it obviously to yourself And make sure you pronounce it correctly Don't say That's completely wrong Right How would you read it Right So that's the main thing So make sure you write that With also the harakat Right Make sure you write And then You get it And I'll just add translate to it So that you know You can just practice So read it Write it Write the harakat at the end And translate it Okay So all these ten You have all the way till Monday So you have some time InshaAllah don't Don't worry too much Dab Dab just means To put the harakat Yeah Awakhir
[SPEAKER_00] means the end Of these words Okay Then number three Imla'il faraq Fee ma'af Fee ma'ali Bi wata'il kalimatil munasiba Min al kalimatil talia Right Imla'il faraq Imla' means to fill Right Imla'il faraq The empty Empty part Al faraq means the empty part Fee ma'ali In whatever follows Bi wata'il kalimatil You don't have to write The exact translation Of the directions I'll explain to you What you need to do Basically You fill in the blanks With whatever word Fits there Right So Al hajaru You see the word Bang on top There's You could say Al hajaru jameel Or al hajaru wasikhun Or al hajaru maftuhun Al hajaru harun Which of these fits With the word Al hajaru Right Saqeel Saqeel Right So that's just The first So we all do it together Just so we know That's You don't say Al hajaru jameelun That this rock is beautiful Unless it really is Like some amazing You know Formation of a rock Or something like that Or has some beautiful Marble design or something But other than that Jameel is not normally used
[SPEAKER_00] For a rock To fit it with there Okay That's to number three Then number four Also You have to fill in the blank But this time It's the other way around Right In the second one You're filling In the first one Number three You're filling in The khabar Meaning you're filling in The second word Which will have what Will it have a tanween Or alif naam on it No In number three The one The previous one Sorry It would It would have In the previous one Number three The one we're looking at I mean the tamreen That we're looking at When you write the word Would you write Al maksoor Or maksoorun Maksoorun Or Or like Thaqeelun You don't say Al thaqeelun Right Because it's the second word Now In the next tamreen The last tamreen You're writing the first word Right So in that case Would you write Al or no al Al Al Right So for example Let's say we're talking about Al
[SPEAKER_00] qameesu Right So al qameesure Is something we just describe As if it's dirty Or clean Right So you would say Al qameesu Nadeefun So you write down Al qamees And likewise You fill in all the other blanks With whatever vocabulary You know In sha Allah Everybody understand the tamreen The homework No Right If you don't understand anything You're free to ask on the group Or you can Call me Or text me Message me individually In sha Allah Sorry Yeah All four So it seems like a lot But don't worry In sha Allah It'll help you To solidify the concepts To help you Practice your writing And also It'll help you remember The vocabulary Right now Learning the vocabulary Is very important Right So everybody make sure You remember all the vocabulary Let's have a We're planning on having Pop quizzes But I think there's no point If nobody actually studies To have a pop quiz So maybe we can have A scheduled quiz Let's see What date Of all the Just vocabulary for now Not the rules
[SPEAKER_00] We'll have a Test for the rules On a later date But just for the vocabulary Let's have a test Very soon Let's have it On November 4th That's not This upcoming Monday But the Monday after that Is that fine Yeah So that'll only be The first 10-15 minutes Of class We'll have a quick quiz And I'll Just collect it from you guys And I'll check it at home Then in sha Allah We'll continue The rest of the class So November 4th Alright Remember there's a Vocabulary quiz Everything that we've learned Everybody got it Yes Okay And the easiest way to know Is just look at The At the end of each lesson It says The new words And then You just have to put all those In one list If somebody wants to do the work Of putting all the words That you learned From the beginning of the book That'll help you And it'll also help Your classmates as well You can just send that Cheat sheet onto the Onto the Group Yeah I found a quiz list That has like The All the words From the In the Oh nice So
[SPEAKER_00] I can Share it In the Yeah That'll be nice That's good Definitely for sure In sha Allah Alright so test Quiz for the Vocabulary on November 4th In sha Allah Alright Now we We got Everybody got the concept In this lesson now Not too difficult right Your brain is not spinning Like last time Everybody's fine Qamrun means Who can tell them What does Qamrun mean Yeah Yeah, the full moon, yeah. We have a question. So can we use the vocabulary page, like in the English part? No, I told you you're not allowed to. We told you that. Not always. I said only last time because we weren't able to go over the vocabulary in class. So I said last time was the exception. But other than that, you're not allowed to use the English side. In the box, it's not always all the words are shown. In the box after number four, one of the words, do you even know that's words? Okay, good point. Brother Abdul Wahab, almost soon to be hafidh inshallah. Abdul Wahab mentioned a good point that
[SPEAKER_00] sometimes they miss, sometimes they miss, shh, you guys keep it down. Sometimes they miss vocabulary in the Kalimatul Jadidah box. So if you want to be thorough, then you look through the whole lesson yourself and make sure there's nothing missing from the Kalimatul Jadidah box and fill it in yourself. Again, if somebody does it all for everybody and puts it all on one list and posts that list in the group, that would help. That would help everybody. That would be very beneficial for everybody inshallah. Otherwise, you can do it individually inshallah. Alright, so we won't go further than this in this lesson inshallah. Now that we have a little bit of time for the... We're going to finish the lesson in the next time inshallah. We have 16, 17, 18, 19. These are all part of the same lesson, third lesson. But it's a different concept so I don't want to go into that yet because we don't have enough time. So I was thinking of going through a few examples from the Quran which can further solidify our understanding of this concept of things being definite and indefinite or what do you call it? Specific or
[SPEAKER_00] unspecific. That same concept, right? So for example, Allah says... Actually Hafiz Sahib recited this in Salah. Hafiz Sahib, he said, لِلَّذِينَ أَحْسَنُوا الْحُسْنَ وَزِيَادَةٌ لِلَّذِينَ أَحْسَنُوا الْحُسْنَ For the people who did good, they get Al-Husna. What is Al-Husna? Al-Husna can be translated to the highest level of reward. Al-Husna means the greatest. If you just translate it literally, it means the greatest. But if you look at the tafsirs, it means the greatest levels of Jannah, basically. Whoever does good gets the greatest. So that's something very specific. That's why Allah says Al-Husna because it's known to everybody. Whoever does something good, they get Al-Husna, which is the highest level of greatness, which is Jannah. So Al-Husna referring to Jannah. So it's referring to something specific which is already known to everybody, the
[SPEAKER_00] readers of the Qur'an. So that's why Allah says Al-Husna. That same reward that you've been promised has been talked about. Then Allah says, وَ... Sorry. Allah says, وَ... زِيَادَتُنْ So this is specific, Al-Husna. And زِيَادَتُنْ is unspecific. So زِيَادَ... For those who know Urdu also, زِيَادَ means something? More. But it means increase. So now, there's a specific reason you see the beauty and the preciseness of the Qur'an, that this is something which is known to everybody. So that's why Al-Husna is used because Jannah is talked about over and over again. It's known. Then زِيَادَ... Allah says, there's so many bounties in Jannah, amazing bounties that we don't even know about. Right? That's why the Hadith mentions, لَتْعَالَىٰ تُنْيَارِ اِبَادِيَ الصَّالِمِينَ I have prepared for
[SPEAKER_00] My pious slaves مَا لَعَيْنِ مُرَأَتَ that which no eye has ever seen وَلَا أُذْرٌ سَمِيعًا that no ear has ever heard of وَلَا خَطَرًا عَلَىٰ قَلْبِ بَشَرٍ and that no heart has ever even thought of, the thought of which has never come onto any heart. Meaning there's so many amazing things that we don't even know about. So that all falls under زِيَادَتُنْ Right? So that shows you why it's unspecific, because it's unknown to us. Right? And there are many things that can be included in that. Sorry? Yeah, exactly. Beyond your imagination. And although there is a Hadith, Sahih Hadith of the Prophet , that mentions that زِيَادَ refers to actually looking at Allah . But in the Mufassirun they explain, they reconcile between the fact that this is تُنْ and they say that it not only includes looking at Allah, but all the other extra things that Allah will give us. So again, that explains why this is unspecific and this is specific. Everybody understood that point? Right? So, beautiful point
[SPEAKER_00] from the Qur'an. And this was recited by Hafez Ta'b in the Salah. So again, I want all of us, especially to pay attention when Hafez Ta'b recited, especially on the class days. Then, for example, in Surah Yaseen, وَجَاءَ أَمِنْ أَقْصَى الْمَيْهِ رَجُلٌ يَسْعَى It's talking about the story of the three prophets that were sent to a specific town. And these prophets were giving da'wah, nobody was accepting them. So then, a person from the furthest part of the city comes, يَسْعَى he comes running. So, the point here is that it's not a known person, it's not one of the three messengers or a specific person that was known in the story before. No. This is a random person that just comes running from the outskirts of the city. So, وَجَاءَ أَمِنْ أَقْصَى الْمَيْهِ رَجُلٌ رَجُلٌ If it was الرَّجُلُ then that would talk about a specific person, but this is رَجُلٌ a random person. And similar wording but slightly different in Sura Qasas. Allah mentioned the story of Musa a.s.
[SPEAKER_00] وَجَاءَ الرَّجُلٌ مِنْ أَقْصَى الْمَيْهِ يَسْعَى This is talking about the story of Musa a.s. now, after he's accidentally killed the man from the Qawm al-Firaـ'ـawn. We know the story. Then, now, he's thinking that okay, but I was a accident so I'm okay. Within a person, A random person It's just to emphasize That it's not a person That was known in the story Or that's known to Musa A.S. It's a random person Came from the furthest part of the city Came running to Musa وَجَاءَ الرَّجُلُ مِنْ أَقْصَى الْمَيَّةِ يَسْعَى Then he told Musa A.S. That they're actually planning So that they can What do you call it? They can kill you Because obviously you killed one of their people Right? So the point is that رَجُلُ It wasn't الرَّجُلُ But it was a random person So it was رَجُلٌ رَجُلٌ Everyone understand that? Yes or no? Okay Then another example Then Okay So now This is the story of Yusuf
[SPEAKER_00] A.S. They're talking to Yusuf A.S. They don't know that Yusuf A.S. is their own brother Right? We know that point where Yusuf A.S. gets that higher status He becomes a governor And Now his brothers are coming Begging to him That you know We don't have any money And the whole story happens With his younger brother How he puts the The cup In his In his bag And then They They say that Oh he was stealing So then They're about to take him in And keep him as a prisoner Even though Yusuf A.S.'s plan was just to bring Him By him And also Thereby bring their entire family Towards him So So anyways So in that whole story We talk about that whole story The The brothers of Yusuf A.S. They're pleading with Yusuf A.S. Because they're thinking That they don't know His father Even though he has the same father They're saying That he has A father He didn't say The father Or our father That would be a specific father Just saying He has a father Because that father Is not known to Yusuf Or they claim They think that he's not known To Yusuf
[SPEAKER_00] A.S. But they don't realize He is known to Yusuf A.S. So he says So the word Is not specific The tanween is there If it was specific It would say Right That father That is known to Yusuf A.S. Or Abana Right That our father Right But He made it unspecific Because I assume That the listener Does not know Everybody got that point? Exactly Alright Then another example Right This is a good example Right Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala In Surah Al-Muzzammil He says إِنَّا أَرْسَلْنَا إِلَيْكُمْ رَسُولًا شَاهِدًا عَلَيْكُمْ كَمَا أَرْسَلْنَا إِلَىٰ فِرَعُونَ رَسُولًا We have sent A messenger To you Talking to people Disbelievers Of Mecca We have sent A messenger to you Who is A Shahidan Who is Shahid over you Then كَمَا أَرْسَلْنَا Just as we have sent To Firaun A Rasul A Rasulan إِلَىٰ فِرَعُونَ رَسُولًا
[SPEAKER_00] Right A messenger Right So it's Allah didn't specify Who that messenger was But then in the next ayah Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala says فَعَصَى فِرَعُونُ The Hufad What does it say? الرَّسُولَ So the word ال Is used Right Because He was already mentioned In the previous ayah So it's as if Now he's known Right He's somebody Who was already mentioned to you So now he's known So that's why ال Is mentioned in the next ayah They're both referring To the same person But the first time He was mentioned It said رَسُولًا And right after that When he was mentioned In the very next ayah فَعَصَى فِرَعُونُ الْرَسُولَ صَوْفِرْعُون He disobeyed The messenger Right I mean that same messenger Who was mentioned to you In the previous ayah So now he's known to you So that's why ال is used Everybody got that point? Yeah exactly They came back with that So it's not رَسُولًا It's رَسُولًا Yeah The very Spreading room Like the Yeah دَمَّة Exactly Because both have the same Annotation Like رَسُولًا Yes
[SPEAKER_00] Exactly Yeah This is what it means in general Right So if it's either It is with دَمَّة Or بَش Or تَنْوِين With فَتْحَة زَبَر Or تَنْوِين With زِر With كَسْرَة In any context This thing will still be there That the تَنْوِين is there to show That it is indefinite And The ضَمَّة Sorry The ال will be there to show That it is something Which is definite and specific Yeah I can't hear you Sorry A little bit louder من and من No no That's different We're getting to من is going to be the next lesson Inshallah So We'll get there Inshallah But this is just for تَنْوِين That we're talking about Okay yeah We're going to end the class here Just one more thing I was trying to Okay we have a couple more examples But it's fine That should be enough For today Oh yeah I wanted to just emphasize that It's good to know that
[SPEAKER_00] Arabic terms For definite and indefinite Right We did mention it last time But let me just mention it again So Definite With دَاوِين Is called بَحَزِيسَة And indefinite means نَكِرَة Okay so just know these terms معرفة means something Which is definite Specific And نَكِرَة means Indefinite So نَكِرَة Generally is Things that have to mean And معرفة Generally things that have We did mention One exception Last time Which was what Very good Mashallah Proper nouns Right Proper nouns are What What are proper nouns Like names
[SPEAKER_00] That refer to specific people Like صَوْا Is a name Or a person Me Right So that Similarly Valley stream Would be a proper noun Because it's a specific place Right So proper nouns Can have تَنْوِين On them And they would still be considered معرفة They would still be considered Definite Because you're talking about A specific person That's an exception So if you don't want to Confuse yourself Right If you're like Oh Alhamdulillah I finally understood everything And now I just brought this thing At the end Don't worry about it Okay Inshallah we'll get there But just know that Proper nouns are An exception to The general rule That تَنْوِين Indicates towards Something which is نَكِرَة Indefinite And I'll refer to things Which are معرفة And that's the end of the class SubhanAllah wa-Ihhamdi Subhanakallah Wa-Ihmani-Kishur Wa-Illa-Illa-Illa Al-Fatiha